Finding Aid for St. Matthew's Episcopal Church, Sparta, Mich., Records, 1955-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Matthew's Episcopal Church, Sparta, Mich., records
1955-2003
St. Matthew's Episcopal Church (Sparta, Mich.)
0649 Ba 2
Saint Matthew's Episcopal Church, located in Sparta, MI, was established 1955 and disbanded in 2003. The record group contains annual reports, bulletins, clergy reports, correspondence, financial records, meeting minutes, newsletters, and various administrative documents.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group came to the library in 2005 as part of the archives of the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Western Michigan (donor no. 5247 ). Additional records were received in 2008.
The record group is open to research.
St. Matthew's Episcopal Church was established in 1955 in Sparta, MI., and it served Sparta's Episcopalian community until its closure in 2003. Before the church's break up, the congregation grew smaller over the years. With fewer people going, church officials conducted surveys of its congregation and analyzed their operating costs. The traditional model of "One Priest, One Parish" was no longer financially viable and too expensive to operate. The church administration started working on an alternative administrative model called Total Ministry. This model encourages baptized members of the congregation to take an active role in the ministry. Instead of the congregation gathered around one minister, everyone in the congregation ministers.
The St. Matthew's Episcopal Church records include annual reports, bulletins, clergy reports, correspondence, financial records, meeting minutes, newsletters, and various administrative documents. The records have been arranged into the following series: Administrative Activities; Bulletins; Financial; Newsletters; Bishops' Advisory Committee; Vestry Meetings; and Registers.
Subjects:
Episcopal Church--Michigan--Sparta.MichiganSparta.; St. Matthew's Episcopal Church (Sparta, Mich.); Sparta (Mich.)--Church history.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (1955-2003) includes annual reports, surveys, correspondence with the Bishop of the Diocese of Western Michigan, and files relating to its planning for, and transition to a "Total Ministry" church.
  - Annual reports, 1955-2003; 18 folders (Box 1)
  - By-laws, 1986-2000 (Box 1)
  - Church information brochures, undated; 2003 (Box 1)
  - Clergy reports, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Diocese of Western Michigan, 1955-1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1960-1987 (Box 1)
  - Incorporation, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Letters of agreement, 1988-2001 (Box 1)
  - Long-range planning, surveys, 1986; 1988; 1990; 1991 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - St. Matthew's Parish Profile, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Search Committee, 1986; 1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Stewardship, 1980-2002 (Box 1)
  - Survey (overhead transparencies), 1982 (Box 1)
  - Total Ministry, correspondence, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
  - Total Ministry, planning, 1994-2003 (Box 1)
  - Total Ministry, transition, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
- Bulletins
  The Bulletin series (1962-2003) contains church programs for distribution to the congregation.
  - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - 1966-1998, 27 folders (Box 2)
  - 1999-2003, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Weddings and Funerals, 1981-1985 (Box 3)
- Financial
  The Financial series (1961-1996) contains records regarding church funding and loans.
  - Applications for financial aid, 1986-1995 (Box 3)
  - Bishop Whittemore Foundation loan application, 1984-1996 (Box 3)
  - Building Fund, 1983-1992 (Box 3)
  - Building Loan, 1961-1973 (Box 3)
  - Discharge of mortgage, 1963-1995 (Box 3)
  - Marrin estate, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Rectory sale, 1994 (Box 3)
- Newsletters
  The Newsletters series (1963-1999) contains monthly newsletters distributed to the congregation.
  - 1963-1976, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - 1980-1999, 19 folders (Box 3)
- Bishop's Advisory Committee Meetings
  The Bishops' Advisory Committee series (1955-1986) is a collection of meeting minutes that contain information about weekly church spending and activities.
  - 1955-1972, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1976-1986, 6 folders (Box 4)
- Vestry Meetings
  The Vestry Meetings series (1985-2003) contain meeting minutes regarding information about weekly church spending and activities. These meetings were attended by congregation members.
  - 1985-2003, 9 folders (Box 4)
- Registers
  The Register series includes volumes containing record of communicants, baptisms, marriages, burials, and confirmations. There are also four volumes of registers of church services with record of attendance, pastor, etc.
  - Church services, 1962-2003; 4 volumes (Box 5)
  - Vital records
    - Combined volume: Communicants 1955-1964 Baptisms, 1955-1973 Confirmations, 1956-1965 Burials, 1955-1985 Marriages, 1960-1979 (Box 5)
    - Combined volume: Baptized persons 1987-2002 Communicants, 1987-2000 Burials, 1987-2003 (Box 5)
    - Confirmations, 1966-1993 (Box 5)
    - Baptisms, 1975-2002 (Box 5)
    - Marriages, 1979-1999 (Box 5)